Guide to the Bruno de Finetti Papers, 1924-2000 ASP.1992.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bruno de Finetti Papers
1924-2000
ULS Archives & Special Collections
De Finetti, Bruno
ASP.1992.01
11.5 Linear Feet (15 large and 6 small document cases, 3 record center cartons of annotated books)
Bruno de Finetti was an Italian probabilist and statistician, noted for the "operational subjective" conception of probability. He provided significant contributions to the theory and the foundations of probability, and his work laid the foundation for the modern subjectivist interpretation of probability. The papers include de Finetti's student notebooks, research papers, lecture and teaching notes, professional and administrative records, newspaper clippings, personal and professional correspondence, and volumes of books from his personal library. Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Biography
Bruno de Finetti was born on June 13, 1906, in Innsbruck, Austria, and died in Rome on July 20, 1985. He began his academic career at the Polytechnic of Milan in 1923 as a student of engineering but later enrolled in the mathematics program at Milan University. While still an undergraduate student, he published his first paper in the area of biomathematics titled "Mathematical Considerations Regarding Mendelian Heredity."
After completing his degree in applied mathematics in 1927, he joined the newly formed Italian census bureau, Istituto centrale di statistica (ISTAT), in Rome. In 1930 he obtained a position as an assistant professor in mathematical analysis at the University of Trieste. One year later he also started working at the insurance company "Assicurazioni Generali" in Trieste on the company's system automation with IBM machines while at the same time teaching calculus of probability at the University of Trieste. In 1936 he entered the competition for the chair of financial mathematics and statistics. Although finishing first place, he was not nominated due to a fascist law denying access to this position to unmarried candidates. Eventually, in 1950, he was appointed ordinary professor at the University of Trieste, effective retroactively to the year 1942. In 1954 he accepted a call to the faculty of economy and commerce at the University of Rome and transferred in 1961 to the chair of calculus of probability at the faculty of mathematical, physical, and natural sciences. De Finetti stayed at the University of Rome until his retirement in 1976. He died in Rome on July 20, 1985.
De Finetti provided significant contributions to the theory and foundation of probability, both from methodological and philosophical points of view. His concept of subjective probability evolved as a result of his profound interest in the application of logical theories, such as the application of mathematics to actuarial questions, to the statistics of insurance, and to the organizational techniques of public administration.
De Finetti also pioneered the concept of "exchangeability" or "exchangeable events." With the introduction of this model, he discovered a way of connecting the notion of subjective probability with the traditional procedures of statistical inference. De Finetti developed his ideas on subjective probability in the 1920s independently of Frank P. Ramsey. He only became known in the Anglo-American statistical world in the 1950s when L. J. Savage introduced his writings.
Arrangement
The papers were divided into six series. Each series is then divided into one or more subseries according to subject area. More detailed scope and content notes are also available at the series level.
Series I. Educational Records
Series II. Professional Activities
Series III. Research
Series IV. Correspondence
Series V. Personal Interests
Series VI. Writings by de Finetti and Others.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers include de Finetti's student notebooks, research material, lecture and teaching notes, professional and administrative records, newspaper clippings, personal and professional correspondence, and books from his working library. The majority of the documents are in Italian and some are in English, French, and German.
The papers, mainly covering the years 1930-1985, are organized into several series and subseries according to subject matter. Original folders, created by de Finetti, are indicated by headings in quotation marks. Sometimes an inventory sheet by Fulvia de Finetti can be found at the beginning of these folders.
De Finetti's educational records (Series I) consist of notebooks and loose notes from his student days at the University of Milan during the years 1924-1927.
Documents comprised under "Professional Activities" (Series II) concern his involvement in numerous professional organizations, in academic business, and in publication projects. Topics include de Finetti's job applications at various institutions, academic business at the University of Trieste and Rome, and his membership on the scientific board of Statistica and in Accademia dei Lincei.
Bruno de Finetti's research papers (Series III) consist largely of notes, drafts, and typescripts, representing his scientific and academic work as well as its application in such projects as the development of a unified coding system for government records. Also documented is his participation in various national and international conferences and workshops. Major research topics featured in this series are probability theory, probability calculus, statistics, actuarial science, game theory, subjective probability, Bayes' theorem, and mathematics applied to economics.
The correspondence (Series IV) illustrates primarily de Finetti's research and academic activities. Noteworthy correspondents are, among others, Oskar Morgenstern, George Polya, Antonio Gennaro, Luciano Daboni, Dennis Lindley, Jerzy Neyman, Siro Lombardini, Pierpaolo Luzzatto-Fegiz, and Jimmie Savage. General events discussed are research by de Finetti and others, mutual exchange of papers and related comments, and de Finetti's publication and teaching projects. The material is arranged alphabetically according to correspondent and then chronologically within folders. However, please note that many pieces of correspondence can also be found in de Finetti's original, subject-related folders throughout the collection, which were not removed in order to preserve the original arrangement.
Series V documents de Finetti's personal interests such as his involvment in school reform and teaching methodology, his political activism, and related legal problems. A wide variety of materials illustrate de Finetti's efforts to improve science and mathematics teaching, teacher education, and school curricula. Subjects discussed are writings by de Finetti such as Il "saper vedere" in matematica and "Perchè la matematica?" de Finetti's plans for educational movies, and a project for an educational center for teachers. Numerous letters, memoranda, newspaper clippings, articles, and court documents give evidence of de Finetti's political and social activism. Documented are his memberships in the fascist party, his participation in the Movimento Politico Lavoratori (MPL), and his role as editor of the Radical Party's publication Notizie Radicali.
A collection of writings by de Finetti and others, mostly in form of offprints and typescripts, sometimes accompanied by related correspondence, is compiled under the last series (Series VI). These writings illustrate his lifelong political and social engagement on subjects ranging from domestic and foreign politics to ethics, politics of language, sustainable development, and Italian bureaucracy, just to name a few. In addition, annotated books from his library document his research work and his comments on the literature.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Bruno de Finetti's daughter, Fulvia de Finetti, Rome, Italy, January 1992, February 1993, and February 1994.
Previous Citation
Bruno de Finetti Papers, 1924-2000, ASP.1992.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Lecture notes; Personal correspondence; Game theory; Bayesian statistical decision theory; Economics, Mathematical; Mathematical statistics; Probabilities; Philosophy; Offprints; Manuscripts for publication; De Finetti, Bruno -- Archives; Accademia nazionale dei Lincei; Daboni, Luciano; De Gennaro, Antonio; Lindley, D. V. (Dennis Victor); Lombardini, Siro; Luzzatto Fegiz, Peirpaolo; Morgenstern, Oskar; Neyman, Jerzy; Pólya, George; Savage, Leonard J.; Università degli studi di Trieste -- Faculty; Università di Roma -- Faculty
- Educational Records, 1924-1927; I.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains notebooks from de Finetti's early student days. The bound notebooks contain loose notes and manuscripts by de Finetti, written in Italian and German, on geometry, mechanics, mathematical analysis, solved mathematics and engineering problems (possibly homework), and notes on lectures by Oscar Chisini, Guilio Vivanti, and Umberto Cisotti.
  - Student Notebooks 1, 1924-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Student Notebooks 2, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Calcolo Vettoriale", 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mathematical Notes, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Professional Activities, 1929-1987; II.
  Series II has been divided into three subseries: 1. Academics and Academic Business (1929-1983), 2. Professional Organizations and Activities (1934-1986), and 3. Publishing Activities (1937-1987).
  The first subseries (Academics and Academic Business) mainly concerns de Finetti's activities in the academic environment such as teaching, university politics and reform, research funding, and job applications. It also includes material on his appeal against the denied appointment to the chair of financial mathematics at the University of Trieste in 1942.
  Material in the second subseries (Professional Organizations and Activities) relates largely to de Finetti's membership in professional and scientific organizations, such as the Accademia dei Lincei, his collaboration with professional journals, and his participation at various conferences.
  The third subseries (Publishing Activities) features correspondence with publishers, friends, and colleagues, page proofs, drafts, reviews, offprints, and related legal material.
  - Academics and Academic Business, 1929-1983; 1.
    - "Curriculum Vitae Elenchi pubbl. Libera docenza ecc." "Concorso Cattedra R. Un. Trieste Mat. Fin. 1939/XVII", 1929-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "de Finetti-Filadelfo Insolera", 1935-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Annullamento Cattedra", 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Università Trieste", 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Tribunato", 1943-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Trasferimento prof. Ugo Morin", 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Corrispondenza insegnamento a Trieste", 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Consiglio di Facoltà", 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Università Trieste", 1946-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Altri parenti", 1948-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Trasf. Roma Concorso 1951", 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - ARAU (Associazione Romana Assistenti Universitari), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - University of Ancona Building Renovation, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - University of Rome Building Renovation, no date (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - University of Rome: Administrative Academic Business, 1946-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - De Finetti's Scientific Biography and Bibliography, 1964-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Professional Organizations and Activities, 1934-1986; 2.
    - "Collaborazione Riviste Congressi - ecc.", 1936-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Univ. Studi Ancona", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Congresses and Meetings, 1934-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "'Statistica' e Gruppo 'Labriola'", 1943-1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Recommendations for Japan Prize, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Lincei", 1963-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Accademia dei Lincei, 1963-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Scientific Associations, 1935-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Publishing Activities, 1937-1987; 3.
    - "Mat. Log. Intuit", 1943-1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Hierche", 1954-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Un mat. e l'economia: originali - [illegible]", 1956-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Savage Saper Vedere", 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Saper vedere traduz.", 1971-1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Th. Decision", 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The Making of Statisticians, 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Publishing Activities, 1944-1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "Recensioni", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Book Reviews and Articles by de Finetti and Others, 1955-1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "Ringraziamenti e critiche su Matematica Logica-Intuitiva", 1943-1948 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Dialectica", 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Index Cards of de Finetti's Publications, 1926-1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Lists of de Finetti's Publications, 1976, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Publication Ads, Abstracts, and Indexes, 1946-1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Research, 1927-2000; III.
  Series III covers de Finetti's research activities. Five research areas were identified and are divided into following subseries: 1. Probability Theory and Statistics, 2. Philosophy of Probability Theory and Philosophy of Science, 3. Applied Research, 4. Actuarial Science, and 5. Writings and Teachings in Economics.
  - Probability Theory and Statistics, 1928-1983; 1.
    Featured are many drafts and typescripts by de Finetti and others, lecture and teaching notes; correspondence with Beniamino Segre, Herman Chernoff, Ennio Persico, Antonino Gennaro, Francesco Paolo Cantelli, and Jimmie Savage; and contributions to various conferences and workshops.
    - "Eventi dipendenti (Equivalenti, ecc)", 1928-1933 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Funz. aleatorie", 1927-1938 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Logica insiemi assiomatica", 1938-1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Articles and Typescripts by de Finetti and Others on Applied Mathematics, Statistics, and Probability, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Concetti per lo studio delle distribuzioni", 1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "College Entrance", 1960-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Chernoff", 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Notes on Probability, 1959-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Probabilità Padova 1937", 1933-1944 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Teaching of Probability Theory At the University of Trieste, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Course on Probability Calculus at the University of Padova, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "Dispense Padova: Corrispondenza e appunti dal 1939 Antonino Gennaro ecc.", 1939-1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Course Notes on Probability Calculus, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Bressanone Workshop: Notes from Lectures by de Finetti and Jimmie Savage, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - De Finetti's Lecture at the Istituto Universitario Studi Europei in Turin, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Course on Probability Theory at the Politecnico di Milano, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Londra 1969", 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Seminar "Matematica Finanziaria ed Attuariale" and Notes on Probability Calculus, 1959, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Annotated page proofs of "Sul modo di scegliere le probabilità' iniziali" by de Finetti and Jimmie Savage, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Annotated page proofs of "The Ability of Different Response and Scoring Methods to Discriminate Levels of Partial Knowledge on a Test Item" by de Finetti, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Annotated article by de Finetti "Bayesianism: Its Unifying Role for Both the Foundations and the Applications of Statistics", 1973 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - De Finetti's Remarks at the Conference on the Foundations of Statistical Inference, Florence, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Page Proofs of Probabilità e induzione - Induction and Probability (Part 1-3) by de Finetti, no date (Box 5, Folder 23-25)
    - "Sull' impostazione assiomatica c.d.p.", 1942, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - "Documentazione per il Prof. de Finetti", 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Mathematical Notes on Statistics, Game Theory, and Probability Theory, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "Francia", 1931-1941 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - "Diversi", 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "Chernoff", 1961 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Concorso pronostici calcio: Experiments on Personal Estimates of Probability, 1961-1969 (Box 5, Folder 32-34)
    - Ultrafiltri, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Notes on Probability, Prevision, and Prediction, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Reviews of de Finetti's Works, 1937, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Philosophy of Probability Theory Philosophy of Science, 1927-2000; 2.
    This subseries contains many lectures notes, drafts, and discussions on research papers with, among others, R.M. Frechet, Jerzy Neyman, Jimmie Leonard Savage, Leon Henkin, I.J. Good, George Polya, Stanislav Ulam, and Franz Kutschera.
    - "Centro studi metodologici Torino 1949" (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Logica plurivalente", 1927-1935 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Congrès International de Philosophie des Sciences, Paris, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Unesco", 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Henkin 1956" (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Psicologia e probabilità", 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "Half-Baked Ideas Per Good", 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Poppi 1966" (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Norges", 1970, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Accademia dei Lincei Lectures: "La probabilità, ossia 'del ragionamento plausibile'", 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Probab. Concez. Moderna - Conf. Sem. Mat.", no date (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Probability: Philosophy and Interpretation. An Article for the International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences.", 1963, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Various Writings on Probability by de Finetti, 1970-1977 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "Miei scritti", 1976-1983 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Article on Probability for Enciclopedia Einaudi, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Notes on Interpretations of Probability, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "Einaudi: Probabilità capitolo II (fotocopia)", 1979 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Ulam 1963-64", 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "Loinger:" Correspondence with A. Loinger and Luigi Lugiato, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "Kutschera-Stegmüller-Hamburg", 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Applied Research, 1930-1976; 3.
    Material comprised in this subseries documents de Finetti's work in applied research, often in projects of the public and private sector such as business mechanization and administrative computer applications, as well as soccer betting, and in discussions at various workshops and conferences. It also features correspondence with Beniamino Segre, Mauro Picone, and Mario Dolcher.
    - "IBM AG TS-VB:" IBM Seminar on Mechanization of Insurance Companies held at Blaricum, October 29-31, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "Teddington 1953:" Symposium on Digital Computation held at Teddington, London, March 1953 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "Ministero Finanze:" Project on Unified Coding System for Government and Tax Records, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - "Varie E 42 calcio:" Algorithm for a Soccer Championship Calendar and contest to improve Rome's Public Transportation System, 1931-1939 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Article "Stratificazioni convesse", 1949 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - De Finetti's Research Proposal on Electronic Computing, Article on Mathematics and Science Education, and his Appointment as Court Expert, no date (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - "Analisi: periodi PICONE:" Picone's Work on Harmonic Analysis, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "Lange:" de Finetti's Contribution to Memorial Lectures on Cybernetic and System Behavior in Honor of Oskar Lange, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - De Finetti's Entry on Mathematics for Enciclopedia Garzanti and Project for Mathematics Textbook, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "Dispense Analisi TS.:" Three Course Packets by de Finetti, Mario Daboni, and Mario Dolcher and Academic Business at the University of Trieste, 1946-1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - "Filosofia:" De Finetti's Notes and Correspondence on Philosophical Subjects such as Freedom of Will, Ethics, Epistemology, Human Nature, Mind-Body Problem, and Discussion of Kant's Work, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
    - Convegno di studi di scienza dell' administratizione, Varenna, 26-29 Settembre 1955: Conference on Public Administration Studies, Varenna, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - "Centro Risc.:" Creation of a Centro Riscossioni (Centris), a Unified and Automated Center for Collecting Customer Payments for Commercial Institutions, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - "Centro Riscossioni SEIM:" Creation of a Unified and Automated Center for Collecting Customer Payments for Commercial Institutions, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - "Dispense corso bancario:" Course on Banking Taught by de Finetti at the University of Rome, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Actuarial Science, 1930-1964; 4.
    Included here are documents on research activities in actuarial sciences such as risk measurement for insurance companies, and financial analysis, accounting, and statistics applied to actuarial sciences; and correspondence with Francesco Paolo Cantelli, Ignazio Messina, Michele Sulfina, Giulio Vivanti, Valentino Arangio-Ruiz, Cesare Bellini, Piero Platone, Riebesell, Guido Marchesini, Francesco Santoro Passarelli, Antigono Donati, Mauro Picone, Gaetano Pietra, Servadei, Fortunati, Ennio Persico, D'Albergo, Filippo Sibirani, Ciocca, and Marcello Signori.
    - "Rischio Pieni 1931/IX-1938/XVI; Concorso CNR 1939:" CNR (Centro nazionale delle ricerche) Award for de Finetti's Article "Il problema dei pieni.", 1930-1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Sindicati:" Material on Social Security for Workers and Insurance for Layoff Compensation, 1933-1935 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Il problema della perequazione:" de Finetti's Lecture for a SIPS (Società italiana per il progresso delle scienze) Congress at Naples, on "perequazione", a Statistical Technique to Manipulate Raw Data and Make It More Homogeneous, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - XIIIième Congrès International d'Actuaires à Amsterdam, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Typscript "Abozzi di stelloncini per la 'Rassegna' " by de Finetti, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Notes on Insurance, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Corsi professionali", 1938-1940 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Accademia Lincei:" INA Award for Actuarial Sciences to de Finetti and Guiseppe Ottaviani, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "Calcolo delle probabilità, Processi aleatori, Numeri aleatori in generale.", 1941-1944 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Writings and Teachings in Economics, 1930-1978; 5.
    Typescripts, manuscripts, course syllabi, discussion transcriptions, and correspondence primarily document de Finetti's contributions to the field of economics, his participations at various conferences, and his teaching activities. Discussion transcripts record debates between de Finetti, Valli, Ulisse Gobbi, Sergio Bruno, and Figà-Talamanca; and between Malinraud, Durbin, Zellner, Savage, and de Finetti. Among correspondents are Benedetto Barberi, Ugo Amaldi, Carlo Picotti, Francesco Paolo Cantelli, Manlio Udina, Gian Antonio Maggi, Giorgio Colombo, Carlo Fabrizi, Federico Chessa, Bruno Sicherl, Tullio Levi-Civita, Giulio Vivanti, and Giuseppe Guadagnini.
    - "Fenomeni da studiare o problemi da risolvere:" Various Writings by de Finetti on Economics and Circulation of de Finetti's Il tragico sofisma, 1934-1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Writings on Mathematics Applied To Economics, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 2)